One in four people suffer from some sort of mental illness,
واحد من كل أربعة أشخاص يعاني من مرض عقلي ما
so if it was one, two, three, four, it's you, sir.
إذا، إذا كان واحد، اثنين، ثلاثة، أربعة، انه أنت، يا سيدي
You. Yeah. (Laughter)
أنت، نعم أنت
With the weird teeth. And you next to him. (Laughter)
صاحب الأسنان الغريبة وأنت إلى جانبه
You know who you are.
أنت تعرف من أنت
Actually, that whole row isn't right. (Laughter)
في الحقيقة هذا الصف كله ليس صحيحاً
That's not good. Hi. Yeah. Real bad. Don't even look at me. (Laughter)
هذا ليس جيداً، أهلاً، نعم جداً سيئة لا تنظر إلي حتى
I am one of the one in four. Thank you.
أنا واحدة من الواحد من كل أربعة، شكراً
I think I inherit it from my mother, who,
أعتقد أني ورثتها من والدتي
used to crawl around the house on all fours.
التي كانت تزحف في المنزل على أطرافها الأربعة
She had two sponges in her hand, and then she had two
كان تمسك أسفنجتين في يديها
tied to her knees. My mother was completely absorbent. (Laughter)
وأثنين مربوطة في ركبتيها،أمي كانت بالكامل ماصّة
And she would crawl around behind me going,
وهي تزحف خلفي وتقول
"Who brings footprints into a building?!"
"من الذي يجلب آثار الأقدام إلى المبنى!؟"
So that was kind of a clue that things weren't right.
لذلك كان هذا دليلاً أن الأمور لم تكن صحيحة
So before I start, I would like to thank
لذلك قبل أن أبدأ أود أن أشكر
the makers of Lamotrigine, Sertraline, and Reboxetine,
صنّاع لاموتريجين و سيترالين و ريبوكسيتين
because without those few simple chemicals, I would not be vertical today.
لأنه بدون هذه الأدوية البسيطة لم أكن واقفة اليوم
So how did it start?
إذا كيف بدأت؟
My mental illness -- well, I'm not even going to talk about my mental illness.
مرضي العقلي، أنا حتى لن أتكلم عن مرضي العقلي
What am I going to talk about? Okay.
عن ماذا سأتحدث اليوم؟ حسناً
I always dreamt that, when I had my final breakdown,
أنا دائماً أحلم عندما يحصل انهياري العصبي الأخير
it would be because I had a deep Kafkaesque
سيكون السبب أنه كان لدي كافكا الغرائبي عميق
existentialist revelation,
الوجودية والوحي
or that maybe Cate Blanchett would play me and she would win an Oscar for it. (Laughter)
أو ربما أن كيت بلاشيت مثلت دوري وسوف تنجح بالحصول على الأوسكار
But that's not what happened. I had my breakdown
لكن هذا لم يحدث، حصل انهياري العصبي الأخير
during my daughter's sports day.
في يوم ابنتي الرياضي
There were all the parents sitting in a parking lot
كان كل الأباء يجلسون في باحة وقوف السيارات
eating food out of the back of their car -- only the English --
يتناولون الطعام في الجزء الخلفي من سياراتهمفقط الإنجليز
eating their sausages. They loved their sausages. (Laughter)
يأكلون السجق، هم يحبون السجق
Lord and Lady Rigor Mortis were nibbling on the tarmac,
السيد والسيدة ريجور كانا على الممر
and then the gun went off and all the girlies started running,
بعد ذلك أطلق الرصاص وبدأ الفتيات في الجري
and all the mummies went, "Run! Run Chlamydia! Run!" (Laughter)
و صرخت كل الأمهات "اجري! اجري كلاميديا!"
"Run like the wind, Veruca! Run!"
"اجري مثل الريح فوروكا! اجري"
And all the girlies, girlies running, running, running,
ثم كل الفتيات يجرين يجرين يجرين
everybody except for my daughter, who was just standing
الجميع ما عدا ابنتي التي كانت واقفة
at the starting line, just waving,
في خط البداية وتلوّح
because she didn't know she was supposed to run.
لأنها لم تكن تعلم أنه يتوجب عليها الجري
So I took to my bed for about a month, and when I woke up
لذلك أخذت إلى سريري لمدة شهر تقريبا، وعندما استيقظت
I found I was institutionalized, and when I saw the other inmates,
لقد وجدت أني في المستشفىوعندما رأيت مرضى آخرين
I realized that I had found my people, my tribe. (Laughter)
أدركت أنني قد وجدت شعبي، قبيلتي (ضحك)
Because they became my only friends, they became my friends,
لأنهم أصبحوا أصدقائي الوحيدينأصبحوا أصدقائي
because very few people that I knew -- Well, I wasn't
لأن الناس القليلين الذين عرفتهمحسناً ، لم أعرفهم
sent a lot of cards or flowers. I mean, if I had had a broken leg
أرسلوا الكثير من البطاقات والورود.أعني أنه له كانت ساقي كسرت
or I was with child I would have been inundated,
أو كنت مع طفل غمرته
but all I got was a couple phone calls telling me to perk up.
لكن كل ما حصلت عليه كان اتصالين تخبرني أن أرفع رأسي
Perk up.
أرفع رأسي
Because I didn't think of that. (Laughter)
لأني لم أكن أفكر في ذلك(ضحك)
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Because, you know, the one thing, one thing that you get with this disease,
لأنه، أنتم تعلمون، الشيء الوحيد الذي تحصل عليه مع هذا المرض
this one comes with a package, is you get a real sense of shame,
هذا يأتي مع المجموعة هو حصولك على إحساس الخجل
because your friends go, "Oh come on, show me the lump,
لأن أصدقائك سيقولون "هيا دعينا نشاهد الورم،
show me the x-rays," and of course you've got nothing to show,
دعينا نشاهد الأشعة السينية" وبالطبع ليس لديك شيء تجعلهم يشاهدونه
so you're, like, really disgusted with yourself because you're thinking,
إذا أنت تكون مشمئز من نفسك لأنك تفكر
"I'm not being carpet-bombed. I don't live in a township."
"أنت لا تكون مغطى بالسجاد، أنا لا أعيش في مدينة متحضرة"
So you start to hear these abusive voices, but you don't hear one abusive voice,
إذا أنت تبدأ تسمع الأصوات المؤذية لكنك لا تسمع صوت مؤذي واحد
you hear about a thousand -- 100,000 abusive voices,
أنت تسمع ألف صوت مؤذيمئة ألف صوت مؤذي
like if the Devil had Tourette's, that's what it would sound like.
كما لو أنه كان الشيطان توريتهكذا يكون الصوت
But we all know in here, you know, there is no Devil,
لكننا كلنا نعلم هنا، أنتم تعلمونأن لا يوجد شيطان
there are no voices in your head.
لا يوجد أصوات داخل رأسك
You know that when you have those abusive voices,
أنتم تعلمون عندما تسمع هذه الأصوات المؤذية
all those little neurons get together and in that little gap
كل هذه الخلايا العصبية الصغيرة تجتمع معاً وفي الفراغ الصغير
you get a real toxic "I want to kill myself" kind of chemical,
تحصل على السم الحقيقي "أريد أن أقتل نفسي" نوع من الادوية
and if you have that over and over again on a loop tape,
و عندما تحصل عليه مراراً في شريط متكرر
you might have yourself depression.
من الممكن أن يحدث لك الاكتئاب
Oh, and that's not even the tip of the iceberg.
وهذا ليس حتى قمة الجبل الجليدي
If you get a little baby, and you abuse it verbally,
إذا كان لديك طفل صغير وأعتديت عليه لفظياً
its little brain sends out chemicals that are so destructive
دماغه الصغير يرسل هذه المواد الكيميائية المدمرة
that the little part of its brain that can tell good from bad just doesn't grow,
هذا الجزء الصغير من دماغه الذي يحدد الصح من الخطأ لم ينمو بعد
so you might have yourself a homegrown psychotic.
لذلك من الممكن أن تسبب لنفسك محلية ذهنية
If a soldier sees his friend blown up, his brain goes into
إذا رأى الجندي صديقه في انفجار، دماغه يتجه إلى
such high alarm that he can't actually put the experience into words,
كما لو أنه في الحقيقة لا يستطيع أن يعبر عن ما حدث
so he just feels the horror over and over again.
لذلك يحصل على إحساس الرعب مراراً وتكراراً
So here's my question. My question is, how come
إذا هنا سؤالي، سؤالي هو
when people have mental damage, it's always an active imagination?
كيف يكون عندما يحصل الناس على خلل عقلي ويحصلون على خيال فعّال؟
How come every other organ in your body can get sick
كيف يكون أي عضو في جسمك مُعرّض للمرض
and you get sympathy, except the brain?
وتحصل على التعاطف، ماعدا الدماغ؟
I'd like to talk a little bit more about the brain,
أنا أود الحديث أكثر قليلاً عن الدماغ
because I know you like that here at TED,
لأني أعلم أنكم تحبون ذلك هنا في TED،
so if you just give me a minute here, okay.
لو تعطون لي دقيقة هنا، حسناً
Okay, let me just say, there's some good news.
حسناً دعوني أقول هناك بعض الأخبار الجيدة
There is some good news. First of all, let me say,
هناك بعض الأخبار الجيدةأولاً دعوني أقول
we've come a long, long way.
نحن حضرنا من طريق طويل
We started off as a teeny, teeny little one-celled amoeba,
لقد بدأنا بوصفها صغيرة، صغيرة قليلا وحيدة الخلية الأميبا
tiny, just sticking onto a rock, and now, voila, the brain.
صغيرة، فقط تلصق في الصخر، والأن هذا هو الدماغ
Here we go. (Laughter)
لقد بدأنا. (ضحك)
This little baby has a lot of horsepower.
هذا الصغير لديه الكثير من القوة الحصانية
It comes completely conscious. It's got state-of-the-art lobes.
وهو يأتي واع تماما. لقد حصلت على فصوص حديثة.
We've got the occipital lobe so we can actually see the world.
لدينا الفص القذالي حتى يمكننا أن نرى في الواقع العالم
We got the temporal lobe so we can actually hear the world.
حصلنا على الفص الصدغي حتى نتمكن من سماع الواقع العالم
Here we've got a little bit of long-term memory,
هنا لدينا قليلا من الذاكرة طويلة المدى
so, you know that night you want to forget, when you got really drunk? Bye-bye! Gone. (Laughter)
لذلك، تعلمون في الليل تريد أن تنسى، عندما تكون في حالة سُكر؟ وداعا وداعا! ذهب. (ضحك)
So actually, it's filled with 100 billion neurons
في الواقع هي ممتلئة بمئة مليار خلية عصبية
just zizzing away, electrically transmitting information,
فقط تزعج، تبتعد المعلومات المحولة كهربائياً
zizzing, zizzing. I'm going to give you a little side view here.
إزعاج، إزعاج. سأعطيكم زاوية رؤية صغيرة هنا
I don't know if you can get that here. (Laughter)
لا أعلم إذا كنتم ستحصلون عليه هنا. (ضحك)
So, zizzing away, and so — (Laughter) —
فقط إزعاج و لكل شخص --(ضحك)
And for every one — I know, I drew this myself. Thank you.
أنا أعلم أنا رسمت هذا بنفسي. شكرا لك.
For every one single neuron, you can actually have
لكل عصب واحد في الواقع يمكن أن تحصلون
from 10,000 to 100,000 different connections
من 10،000 إلى 100،000 اتصالات مختلفة
or dendrites or whatever you want to call it, and every time
أو التشعبات أو ما تريدون أن نسميها، وفي كل مرة
you learn something, or you have an experience,
تتعلمون شيئاً أو تحصلون على خبرة
that bush grows, you know, that bush of information.
هذه الأحراش تنمو، كما تعلمون، ان هذه الأحراش من المعلومات
Can you imagine, every human being is carrying
من الممكن أن تتخيلوا ،كل شخص بشري يحمل
that equipment, even Paris Hilton? (Laughter)
هذه العدة، حتى باريس هيلتون؟ (ضحك)
Go figure.
استقصوا الأمر.
But I got a little bad news for you folks. I got some bad news.
ولكن لدي بعض الأخبار السيئة بالنسبة للناسلديّ بعض الأخبار السيئة
This isn't for the one in four. This is for the four in four.
هذه ليست للواحد من أربعة. بل للأربعة من أربعة
We are not equipped for the 21st century.
نحن غير مهيؤون ونحن في القرن الحادي والعشرين
Evolution did not prepare us for this. We just don't have the bandwidth,
التطور لم يعدّنا لهذا . نحن لا نملك هذه السعة،
and for people who say, oh, they're having a nice day,
وللناس الذين يقولون أنهم يحظون بيوم جيد
they're perfectly fine, they're more insane than the rest of us.
هم بحالة ممتازة، إنهم أكثر جنوناً من بقيتنا
Because I'll show you where there might be a few glitches
لأنني سأريكم أين يمكن أن تكون هناك أخطاء قليلة
in evolution. Okay, let me just explain this to you.
في التطوّر.حسناً، دعوني أشرح لكم هذا
When we were ancient man — (Laughter) —
عندما كنا الانسان القديم-- (ضحك)
millions of years ago, and we suddenly felt threatened
منذ ملايين السنين، وشعرنا فجأة بالتهديد
by a predator, okay? — (Laughter) —
من قبل حيوان مفترس، حسنا؟ -- (ضحك)
we would — Thank you. I drew these myself. (Laughter)
نحن سنفعل...شكراً . أنا رسمت هذا بنفسي .(ضحك)
Thank you very much. Thank you. Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم جزيلاً، شكراً، شكراً. (تصفيق)
Thank you. Anyway, we would fill up with our own adrenaline
شكراً، على أي حال إننا نمتلئ بالأدرينالين الخاص بنا
and our own cortisol, and then we'd kill or be killed,
والكورتيزول الخاص بنا، ومن ثم نقتل أو نتعرض للقتل
we'd eat or we'd be eaten, and then suddenly we'd de-fuel,
نأكل أو نتعرض للأكل وفجأة نعيد الوقود
and we'd go back to normal. Okay.
ومن ثم نعود للوضع الطبيعي، حسناً.
So the problem is, nowadays, with modern man— (Laughter) —
إذا المشكلة في الوقت الحالي في الرجل المتحضر --(ضحك)--
when we feel in danger, we still fill up with our own chemical
عندما نشعر بالخطر نستمر في تعاطي الكيميائيات
but because we can't kill traffic wardens — (Laughter) —
ولكن لأننا لا نستطيع قتل مراقبي المرور --(ضحك)
or eat estate agents, the fuel just stays in our body
أو أكل وكلاء العقارات، يبقى الوقود فقط في جسمنا
over and over, so we're in a constant state of alarm,
مرارا وتكرارا بذلك، نحن في حالة مستمرة من التنبيه
a constant state. And here's another thing that happened.
حالة مستمرة وهنا شيء آخر حدث
About 150,000 years ago, when language came online,
قبل قرابة 150،000 سنة عندما بدأت اللغة
we started to put words to this constant emergency,
بدأنا في وضع الكلمات لهذه الحالة الطارئة المستمرة
so it wasn't just, "Oh my God, there's a saber-toothed tiger,"
لذلك لم يكن مجرد "يا إلهي، هناك نمر ذو أسنان"
which could be, it was suddenly, "Oh my God, I didn't send the email. Oh my God, my thighs are too fat.
كان يمكن أن تكون، فجأة، "يا إلهي، لم ارسل البريد الإلكتروني. يا إلهي، لدي الفخذين سمينين جدا.
Oh my God, everybody can see I'm stupid. I didn't get invited to the Christmas party!"
يا إلهي، يمكن للجميع رؤية أني غبي، لم أحصل على دعوة لحفلة عيد الميلاد! "
So you've got this nagging loop tape that goes
لذلك كنت قد حصلت على هذا الشريط الذي يذهب الحلقة المزعجة
over and over again that drives you insane, so,
مرارا وتكرارا هذا يدفعك للجنون، لذلك
you see what the problem is? What once made you safe
ترى ما هي المشكلة؟ ما كان يجعلك آمنا
now drives you insane.
الآن يدفعك أنت للجنون.
I'm sorry to be the bearer of bad news, but somebody has to be.
أنا آسفة أن أكون الحامل للاخبار السيئة، ولكن لابد من أن يكونها شخص ما.
Your pets are happier than you are. (Laughter)
حيواناتك الأليفة أكثر سعادة مما أنت عليه. (ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So kitty cat, meow, happy happy happy, human beings, screwed. (Laughter)
حتى القط كيتي سعيد سعيد سعيد، والبشر مشدودين. (ضحك)
Completely and utterly -- so, screwed.
تماماً لذلك مشدودين
But my point is, if we don't talk about this stuff,
ولكن وجهة نظري هي، اذا كنا لا نتحدث عن هذه الاشياء
and we don't learn how to deal with our lives, it's not going
ولم نتعلم كيف نتعامل مع حياتنا، الأمر لا يغدو
to be one in four. It's going to be four in four
أن يكون واحد لأربعة. ستصبح أربعة لأربعة
who are really, really going to get ill in the upstairs department.
الذين حقا سيحصول على المرض في أدمغتهم.
And while we're at it, can we please stop the stigma?
وبينما نحن في ذلك، هل يمكننا وقف وصمة العار؟
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً لكم. (تصفيق)
(Applause) Thank you.
(تصفيق) شكراً لكم